<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Keenan's Personal Log</title>
    <description>Project log of things I have done in my free time.</description>
    <link>https://x-axis.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://x-axis.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 21:55:40 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 21:55:40 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Literary Souvenirs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From time to time, I have read poems on graves, scribbled behind bathroom doors, shared in anonymous forums. These have no digital footprint and therefore, because memory is imperfect, they are scribed here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice rhyme scheme and a pleasant cadence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Do not so quick spurn one in plight --
The wheels of Fate so turns
In fashions which grant grim delight
That fortune one day burns.

Do not so quick serve one of light --
As the zealot later learns
The fall of kings and age of night
Is the fate which fervor earns.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is particularly sad and made me cry. I saw it etched into a memorial :(.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I was a traveler
Across the country far and wide
I heard the mountain's testimony
And saw the skies declare his glory

Along the highways I traveled
Till concrete and steel collapsed
Although I was crushed and buried
I am still alive!

But as man's work failed me
My savior stood by me
Remember the works of Jesus Christ
For his love endures forever
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2017/literary-souvenirs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2017/literary-souvenirs</guid>
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Singularity</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Was this the singularity that launch'd a thousand redshifts,
And irradiated the boundless expanse of space?
Sweet Sagittarius, make me immortal with a kiss.
Her mass sucks forth my soul: see where it flies!
Come, A*, come, give me my soul again.
Here will I dwell, for eternity is in these horizons,
And all is infinitesimal that is not Sagittarius A*.
I will be Genzel, and for love of thee,
Instead of Kepler, shall Fermi be sacked;
And I will measure with neighboring S2, 
And prove thy central mass on my orbit;
Yea, I will debunk theories to the contrary,
And then return to Sgr A* for a kiss.
Thou art grander than the Orion Sun
Clad in the remnants of a thousand stars;
Brighter art thou than the x-ray flare
When it appear'd to hapless Chandra;
More lovely than the monarch of the sky
In humbling Scorpius's stingin' scales;
And none but thou shalt be my paramour!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past week, Christopher Marlowe’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://allpoetry.com/The-Face-That-Launch%27d-A-Thousand-Ships&quot;&gt;The Face That Launch’d A Thousand Ships&lt;/a&gt; has been stuck in my head. What a beautiful piece of work, that in adaptation, deserves a subject just as grand and illustrious as Helen of Troy! With this in mind, I penned it for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/chandra/multimedia/black-hole-SagittariusA.html&quot;&gt;Sagittarius A*&lt;/a&gt;, the Galactic Center of the Milky Way. The starry-eyed sentiment of this poem is in no small part due to a new person in my love life. :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2017/singularity</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2017/singularity</guid>
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>World Map Dining Table</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Log last updated: 10/18/2018&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been so long since I’ve posted! I graduated and started working full-time. Moved into a new apartment. Some exciting personal stuff which has been occupying my evenings :). Now that I’ve started to get into a routine, my latest project has been to repurpose my dining table into functional artwork.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2017/world-map-dining-table</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2017/world-map-dining-table</guid>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>logs</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sonnet No. 116</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Let me not to the marriage of true minds  
Admit singularities; continuity is not continuity  
Which alters when it alteration finds,  
Nor does it bend with the remover who removes.

O no, it is an ever-smooth function  
Which looks on tempest, and is never shaken. 
It is the star to every indefinite integral  
Whose area's unknown, although its height be taken.  

Continuity is not Time's fool; though minima and peaks 
Traverse within the bending Euclidean vicinity.
Continuity alters not to its brief hours and weeks,
But bears it out even to the edge of infinity 

If this be wrong, and upon me proved,  
Then I never derived, nor no curve ever smoothed. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inspiration for this followed immediately after reading Sonnet 116 – for what is enduring love, but continuity for all time? So far this draft is just a series of cheap transpositions but I hope to improve on it further some other day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2017/sonnet-116</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2017/sonnet-116</guid>
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sonnet No. 18</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Shall I compare thee to a harmonic series?  
Thou art more lovely and more temperate.  
Rough winds do shake the n'th terms to zeros  
And its divergence hath all too slow a rate.

Sometime to infinity this sequence shines,  
And arbitrarily large are his partials summ'd.  
And every term from term sometime declines  
By chance or nature's changing course, untrimm'd.  

But thy eternal series shall not fade,  
Nor lose possession of that fair limit thou ow'st,  
Nor shall Fourier brag that thou wander'st in his shade,  
When in infinite sums to Time, thou grow'st.  

So long as Cauchy can breathe and Gauss can see,  
So long converges this, and this gives life to thee.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My past few weeks have been filled with Shakespeare and I feel compelled to translate one of his most famous sonnets into mathematics. The difficult part is in maintaining the rhyme and syllable scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The harmonic series is an infinite series which represents the harmonic tones in music. It is often considered “beautiful” in mathematics and is popularly used by architects to define portions and establish harmonic relationships between different spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the number of terms in a harmonic series becomes infinite, the limit of its &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n&lt;/script&gt;‘th term approaches zero. However, despite that fact, the harmonic series is still a divergent series – albeit at an extremely slow rate. The sums of its partial terms become infinitely large even as the value of the next term decreases over time by nature of the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convergent infinite series is used as a representation of the love’s beauty. Like an inifnite series, their beauty shall never fade. As is required of convergence, the series never loses its limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fourier transform is a powerful tool used in harmonic analysis to determine divergence. Gauss and Cauchy also discovered many of the tests used today to determine convergence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as these verses are read, so long lives my love.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2017/sonnet-18</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2017/sonnet-18</guid>
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Somewhere In Infinity</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A line from a faraway coordinate; 
These real-valued constants sketch out limits --
Fated for the two of us to converge.

Derivatives follow the gradient's path;
An infinitesimal moment in time
passes by as we lock our eyes as one.

Over that field, they are all there in sight;
Smooth curves and functions that are beautiful --
I need you to trust all that I can see.

From back in the day when you'd look above
And see the scalars soaring with my love -- 
That we'd be here today was meant to be.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work today, I was listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nA9rMYn-2nE&quot;&gt;Bokura no Natsu no Yume&lt;/a&gt; (translated: &lt;em&gt;Our Summer Dream&lt;/em&gt;) and was inspired to pen this piece instead of reading papers and working on the literature review like I was supposed to. This song is so hopeful and nostalgic and it reminded me of so many childhood memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been reading about iambic pentameter lately so each line has ten syllables.  This poem feels like it’s in the first stages of something larger. The final stanza seems awkward but with some revision, a few more lines, and a rhyme scene, this could someday become a sonnet. Now &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; would be nice :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2017/somewhere-in-infinity</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2017/somewhere-in-infinity</guid>
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Operation HEAR</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Log last updated: 04/17/2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was a kid, I’ve wished for a way to hear while in the water. As of 2016, the only waterproof hearing aid on the market is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.siemens.com/press/en/pressrelease/?press=/en/pressrelease/2012/healthcare/h20121036.htm&quot;&gt;Siemens Aquaris&lt;/a&gt;. Someday I would like one but for now, this is my journal of trying to figure out something more cost-effective :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;12292014&quot;&gt;12/29/2014&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got fitted with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.resound.com/en-US/hearing-aids/enzo2&quot;&gt;Resound Enzo&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This hearing aid has actually been life-changing. As a &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/programs/mfi/&quot;&gt;Made for iPhone®&lt;/a&gt; product, it streams sound from my phone directly into my hearing aid’s internal microphone via Bluetooth. The external microphone can also be disabled, effectively resulting in 100% noise-cancellation. For the first time, I could Skype without having to ask my friends to constantly repeat themselves because the max volume wasn’t loud enough. I looked forward to FaceTiming my family instead of anxiously wishing I could hang up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8052016&quot;&gt;8/05/2016&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Went tubing with my friends! I had taken out my hearing aids for tubing in a lake before, but this trip was a 3-hour trip down a lazy river. We would essentially be chilling and talking the entire time. I didn’t want to be left out so I wore my old pair from high school. I figured that if something happened to them, I’d still have the ReSounds. The trip turned out to be a blast; we tied our tubes together and played music while talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/x9UHNwn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;River tubing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Image from Trinity River Vision Authority.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8182016&quot;&gt;8/18/2016&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hatched crazy idea of using iPhone as a microphone and pairing it to waterproof Bluetooth headphones. Then I simply enclose my iPhone in a waterproof case and swim with it. I had already gotten such a case for tubing and discovered that I could still talk on the phone. That is, my phone’s internal microphone could pick up sound even in a watertight case. Of course, this idea depends on the case staying waterproof and not destroying my phone in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apps that can turn the iPhone into a microphone are many! Preliminary testing using my hearing aids as Bluetooth headphones revealed that the internal iPhone microphone is surprisingly good and can switch between near and far range. I turned off my hearing aid’s external microphone so that the only sound came from the iPhone’s internal microphone. I could hear my parents yelling my name from downstairs and hold a conversation with them in the car and at the dinner table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound quality is extremely polluted. There is a lot of ambient / background noise and it is annoyingly loud. My voice also sounds disturbingly different, I can’t describe it. My parents also sound different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, results are optimistic and this idea looks possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8192016&quot;&gt;8/19/2016&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research waterproof ratings. Apparently they are on an “IPX” scale from 0 (zero protection) to 8 (fully waterproof).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Level&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Protection&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Can withstand water jets at 100 liters/min for 3 min&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Immersion up to 1 meter for 30 minutes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Continuous immersion up to 3 meters&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ordered a pair of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01G8JO5F2/&quot;&gt;IPX7 Bluetooth earbuds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8222016&quot;&gt;8/22/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bluetooth headphones arrive. Comfortable and tightly snug in ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The range is fine, I can hear a “noise” when my parents are yelling my name from downstairs but the sound quality… beyond salvageable. It sharply degrades with distance, with speech intelligibility at 3 feet, but unintelligible beyond 1 meter. It is difficult to discern changes in pitch and tone. These results are puzzling considering how well this worked when I paired my hearing aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further investigation shows that the iPhone is automatically using the microphone in my Bluetooth headphones instead of its own internal microphone. This seems to be the default behavior; there is no existing method to choose which microphone my phone uses. I tried several &lt;a href=&quot;http://petralex.pro/en/article/view?id=1&quot;&gt;hearing algorithms&lt;/a&gt;: Petralax, NAL, Berger, and POGO. I generally prefer POGO, but in all cases the algorithms failed epically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exhaustive search for all IPX6, IPX7, and IPX8 wireless headphones without a built-in microphone. There are none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since trials with my hearing aid worked well, I think this should still work if I can force my phone to use its internal microphone. To be sure, I’ll repeat tests using wired earbuds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8232016&quot;&gt;8/23/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I borrowed my dad’s Apple earbuds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results were even better than expected! As predicted, my iPhone used its internal microphone to pick up audio and routed it through my earbuds. The sound quality was the pleasant surprise. In tests with my hearing aid, I had complained about how annoying the background noise was. Here, there was no background noise simply by virtue of the fact that I couldn’t hear it. My hearing aid is an amplifier that boosts all sound, but normal wired earbuds don’t have such a thing. The only volume control would come from the iPhone, and it turned out that the only sounds I could hear were those considerably above background noise, i.e. loud spoken audio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thoughts were confirmed by this test: I just need to figure out a way to remove the microphone profile from my Bluetooth headphones. That, or find waterproof wired earbuds which might be an easier task. The best wired waterproof earbuds I found (sorted by Amazon rating) are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table id=&quot;EarbudsTable&quot; class=&quot;tablesorter&quot;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Product&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;IPX&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Price&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Rating&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Travelon-Waterproof-Headphones-White-Yellow/dp/B00CBT9K0Y/&quot;&gt;Travelon Headphones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;$13.17&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4.0&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;

	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Baakyeek-Waterproof-Underwater-Swimming-Headphone/dp/B00IIEHZDK/&quot;&gt;Baakyeek Headphones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;$4.59&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4.3&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;

	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Black-Swimbuds-100%25-Waterproof-Headphones/dp/B01BTFHYIU/&quot;&gt;Swimbuds Black&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;$40.00&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4.3&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;

	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Waterfi-SwimActive-Waterproof-Headphones-Technology/dp/B01GW39XII/&quot;&gt;Waterfi SwimActive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;$39.95&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3.6&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;

	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Avantree-Hippocampus-WATERPROOF-Underwater-Headphones/dp/B01GDRC35S/&quot;&gt;Avantree Hippocampus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;$16.99&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;

	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/IEN2-BK-X-Audio-Sportwrap-Waterproof-Headphones/dp/B00AJD0H8I/&quot;&gt;H2O Audio Surge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;$24.99&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3.2&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While looking for earbuds, I found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01243EJ7A/&quot;&gt;waterproof case&lt;/a&gt; that has an armband and a place to plug in earbuds. It also floats! It looks like wired earbuds will be the easiest solution, but I’m still hung up on trying to make this work with Bluetooth. For now I have a couple weeks before I go anywhere so I might as well try. That brings up a new question: what is the underwater range of Bluetooth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preliminary-research&quot;&gt;Preliminary Research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bluetooth is a wireless technology standard that operates on ultra high frequency radio waves. In essence, it transmits signals through electromagnetic radiation but things get tricky when moving from air to water. Signal loss can occur through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transmission loss from reflection and refraction at the air/water boundary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;propagation loss due to water’s high permittivity and electrical conductivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the first case shouldn’t be an issue since my headphones would already be in the water. &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.library.ubc.ca/cIRcle/collections/ubctheses/24/items/1.0220823&quot;&gt;Zeng&lt;/a&gt; does a survey of underwater wireless communication in seawater and finds that scattering is low at long wavelengths like RF (radio frequency), so that leaves the second case. Water’s high permittivity reduces any electric field around it, which is problematic since electromagnetic waves propagate via disturbances in the electric (and magnetic) fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Uyo59pz.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization of EM propagation&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Image from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.physicsclassroom.com/mmedia/waves/em.cfm&quot;&gt;Physics Classroom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radio frequencies like Bluetooth suffer from high attenuation - its intensity decreases sharply upon contact with water molecules. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hydro-international.com/content/article/underwater-electromagnetic-propagation&quot;&gt;Rhodes&lt;/a&gt; explains this process,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Loss is largely due to the effect of conduction on the electric field component. Propagating waves continually cycle energy between the electric and magnetic fields; hence conduction leads to strong attenuation of electromagnetic propagating waves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saltwater has a high conductivity while freshwater has a relatively low conductivity. This means that it’ll be more challenging to engineer a hearing solution for snorkeling in the ocean compared to swimming in a lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Bluetooth has virtually nil connectivity. &lt;a href=&quot;http://file.scirp.org/pdf/JEMAA20110700001_18390291.pdf&quot;&gt;Jiang and Georgakopoulos&lt;/a&gt; show that the optimum frequency for air-to-water communication is short-wave radiowaves in the 3 to 100 MHz range. In contrast, Bluetooth is almost two orders of magnitude bigger, falling under the spectrum of microwaves at 2.4 to 2.4835 GHz. Anyone who’s had a good middle school science teacher will remember that kitchen microwaves heats food by heating the water molecules, which absorbs the microwaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wireless frequencies that do work underwater include sonar and NFC. Apple implemented NFC chips in iPhone 6 for Apple Pay, but have banned access by third party apps. Regardless, it’s a moot point since NFC headphones are so few and not at all waterproof. If I hope to use my phone, then Bluetooth it’ll have to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my purposes, I don’t really &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a big range. If I am swimming with waterproof earbuds, then that’s a max depth of one foot. I am having a REALLY hard time finding out what the underwater Bluetooth range is. You’d think this would be a common question - and it is - but I guess it is so ineffective that few sought to quantify it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8252016&quot;&gt;8/25/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I spent a lot of time looking at forums for R/C submarines and… I am actually kinda appalled by how much misinformation there was. Some posters would attribute the ineffectiveness of Bluetooth to the resonant frequency of water, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.schoolphysics.co.uk/age16-19/Wave%2520properties/Wave%20properties/text/Microwave_ovens/index.html&quot;&gt;which is incorrect&lt;/a&gt;. I didn’t know anything just a few days ago, but it is problematic when veteran posters propagate incorrect information to newbies. Luckily, this is the Internet, and there is always somebody rushing to prove people wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8262016&quot;&gt;8/26/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theoretical-underwater-bluetooth-range&quot;&gt;Theoretical Underwater Bluetooth Range&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still hung up on this underwater Bluetooth range thing. I could make life easier for myself and just go with the wired earbuds but… no. I have about two weeks left of summer vacation and I PROMISED myself that I wouldn’t do any math, but here we go…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radio frequency power is expressed in decibels. Using the formula for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free-space_path_loss&quot;&gt;free-space path loss&lt;/a&gt;, we can calculate the maximum distance (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt;) of a wireless signal as a function of path loss (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;FSPL&lt;/script&gt;), frequency (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt;), and the speed of light in a vacuum (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align} 
\text{FSPL}_{dB} &amp;= 10\log_{10}\left(\left( \frac{4\pi df}{c}\right)^2\right) \\
&amp;= 20\log_{10}(d) + 20\log_{10}(f) + 20\log_{10} \left( \frac{4\pi}{c}\right) \\
&amp;= 20\log_{10}(d) + 20\log_{10}(f) - 147.55
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Actually, this isn’t a good formula, but it was my easiest starting point.) If we measure frequency in GHz instead of Hz, the equation becomes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
\text{FSPL}_{dB} &amp;= 20\log_{10}(d) + 20\log_{10}(f \cdot 10^9) - 147.55 \\ 
&amp;= 20\log_{10}(d) + 20\log_{10}(f) + 20\log_{10}(10^9) - 147.55 \\
&amp;= 20\log_{10}(d) + 20\log_{10}(f) + 32.45
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rearranging the equation above to find distance, we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;d = 10^{\frac{1}{20}\left(FSPL - 20\log(f) - 32.45\right)}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bluetooth frequency is a known value, but what about the path loss? &lt;a href=&quot;http://file.scirp.org/pdf/JEMAA20110700001_18390291.pdf&quot;&gt;Jiang and Georgakopoulos&lt;/a&gt; look at wireless signal loss in fresh water, producing the following graph of propagation loss at various depths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/G8KWKBg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Propagation loss of electromagnetic waves&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A depth of 0.5 m is, in American, 1.6 feet. Bluetooth is around 2.45 GHz and I am not looking to go deep, so the solid line at 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; Hz (or 1 GHz) is what I’m interested in. It looks like the propagation loss is about 25 dB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can substitute values into the equation above to get the theoretical distance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
d &amp;= 10^{\frac{1}{20}\left(25 - 20\log(2.45) - 32.45\right)} \\
&amp;= 0.1731 \text{ m}
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, our theoretical range in freshwater, without accounting for transmission loss, is 17.31 centimeters. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3355409/&quot;&gt;Lloret et al.&lt;/a&gt; achieved Bluetooth connectivity at average depths of 16-17 cm in a swimming pool filled with freshwater. &lt;a href=&quot;http://bib.irb.hr/datoteka/686678.Miskovic_et_al_final_paper.pdf&quot;&gt;Mišković et al.&lt;/a&gt; found that under calm sea conditions, Bluetooth connection can be established at depths of fewer than 15 cm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8252016-1&quot;&gt;8/25/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I have a theoretical (and empirical) distance of Bluetooth range in freshwater, it seems pretty pointless to extend the theoretical result to seawater. 15 cm is about 5.91 inches, so my head would be just under the surface of the water before I lose connectivity. This is still good for my purposes, so I’m going to go ahead with trying to modify the ActivBuds such that my phone stops using the Bluetooth microphone. That will fix the sound quality issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8262016-1&quot;&gt;8/26/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hacking-attempts&quot;&gt;Hacking Attempts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I tried to hack and reprogram my Bluetooth headphones. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01G8JO5F2&quot;&gt;Senso ActivBuds&lt;/a&gt; use Bluetooth v4.0+EDR, which stands for Enhanced Data Rate. Bluetooth devices interact with each other through “profiles,” and the profiles that Apple supports are &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT204387&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It looks like my headset might have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.bluetooth.org/TechnologyOverview/Pages/HFP.aspx&quot;&gt;HFP profile&lt;/a&gt;. Now the question is: do the headphones support the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.bluetooth.org/TechnologyOverview/Pages/A2DP.aspx&quot;&gt;A2DP profile&lt;/a&gt; as with wired headphones?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see which profiles are on my ActivBuds, I downloaded Bluetooth Explorer (in &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/download/more/&quot;&gt;Hardware IO Tools for Xcode&lt;/a&gt;) and paired the ActivBuds to my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Me8oOfO.png&quot; alt=&quot;ActivBuds profiles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the picture above, we see that it supports the HFP protocol (as predicted), but also &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.bluetooth.org/TechnologyOverview/pages/a2dp.aspx&quot;&gt;A2DP Sink&lt;/a&gt;, which is the profile for receiving a digital-audio stream delivered from a source. Later, I realized that music streaming happens over A2DP and you can listen to music with headphones so obviously it must have supported that profile :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some more digging, I suspect that it has a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.csr.com/products/csr8635&quot;&gt;CSR635&lt;/a&gt; chip. According to its &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.csr.com/sites/default/files/csr8635_qfn_technical_overview.pdf&quot;&gt;technical specs&lt;/a&gt;, it has a transmit power of 8 dBm and receiver sensitivity of -89 dBm. &lt;a href=&quot;http://electronicdesign.com/communications/understanding-wireless-range-calculations&quot;&gt;ElectronicDesign&lt;/a&gt; calculates wireless range using these two numbers but I don’t feel like recalculating anymore. The author does use the FSPL formula that I used, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/d7ceqLJ.png&quot; alt=&quot;ActivBuds Bluetooth protocols&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the picture above, we see the following protocols:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth#AVDTP&quot;&gt;AVDTP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: used to stream music to stereo headsets over an L2CAP channel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth#RFCOMM&quot;&gt;RFCOMM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: generates a serial data stream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth#AVCTP&quot;&gt;AVCTP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: used by the remote control profile to transfer AV/C commands, e.g. music control buttons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all I’ve found so far for today. I don’t know anything about engineering so it’s taken a lot of time reading through documentation and figuring out what to look for. I haven’t found a guide that tells you how profiles get put on Bluetooth “modules” (chips) – there might not even be one. I’m feeling pretty discouraged about being able to hack my ActivBuds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;turn-of-events&quot;&gt;Turn of Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the bright side, waterproof case showed up today! In the photo below, you can see that it is buoyed by the inflated borders. It also has a line-in for wired earbuds and they worked pretty well. Then I wondered if the iPhone would stay in A2DP profile if I plugged in my Apple earbuds while having the Senso ActivBuds paired. The answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/NU8twwP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Smarco Waterproof Case&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then all of a sudden, I heard my mom talking on the phone! While the ActivBuds were in! I paid attention and realized I could distinguish what she was saying. Until now, I had only been testing these things by listening to NPR Radio and TED Talks from my computer at max volume and it was impossible to make out anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I was using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/petralex-hearing-aid/id816133779&quot;&gt;Petralex&lt;/a&gt; amplifier which actually gives you a hearing test first and then “fits” the amplification using several proprietary algorithms: Petralex, NAL, Berger, and POGO. I don’t know what the differences are but find that Berger and POGO perform best with higher pitches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, I had been using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/hearyounow-your-personal-sound/id569522474&quot;&gt;HearYouNow&lt;/a&gt; app and I couldn’t understand my mom with these. However, this app performed best with the Apple earbuds. Really interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I might not have to do any tweaking on the ActivBuds after all. Tomorrow morning I’m going to visit my mom’s workplace and I’m going to try the ActivBuds again with the Petralex app in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8282016&quot;&gt;8/28/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday night, I went to a party and tried the ActivBuds/Petralex combo. It was actually quite good. We played board games and I could more or less keep up with the overlapping chatter. It is unclear why I can understand live human speech, but not speech from my computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I got in touch with a hardware engineer who specializes in embedded stuff and hardware/software interactions and he cleared up a lot of things for me. (If you’re reading this, you’re great!) We discussed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bragi.com&quot;&gt;The Dash&lt;/a&gt; smart earphone that he owns, which are also IPX7. It has an &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.bragi.com/hc/en-us/articles/203178271-Adjust-volume-and-audio-transparency&quot;&gt;Audio Transparency&lt;/a&gt; mode which amplifies the sounds of the ambient environment with a Master Volume setting. That was interesting, since it’s essentially what I’ve been trying to do. However, the Dash still uses the microphone internal to the Dash as the transparency feature’s signal doesn’t go to the phone over Bluetooth. Ultimately, the device has a lot of promise but doesn’t do as well on the connectivity and amplification side so I would not get it (and it’s $300).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also discussed viable paths forward in my own project. Trying to modify the Bluetooth chip is hopeless, as the profiles are controlled by proprietary firmware. If anything, you would write a software that interfaces with the profiles that the chip supports. As a result, I am better off trying to write my own app would stream real-time audio from my iPhone’s via A2DP. Conceptually, it shouldn’t be difficult. I don’t see why streaming from a microphone to headphones is any different from streaming to a speaker and there are plenty of those apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s documentation in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/AudioVideo/Conceptual/MultimediaPG/UsingAudio/UsingAudio.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP40009767-CH2-SW6&quot;&gt;iOS Developer Library&lt;/a&gt; with sample source code for &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/samplecode/aurioTouch/Introduction/Intro.html&quot;&gt;aurioTouch&lt;/a&gt;. Also found &lt;a href=&quot;https://audiostream.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;Audiostream&lt;/a&gt;. Commercially, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.binpress.com/app/radiotunes-sdk/596&quot;&gt;RadioTunes SDK&lt;/a&gt; looks pretty neat.
I’ve found a couple old threads, &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.unity3d.com/threads/real-time-audio-from-microphone.145686/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.unity3d.com/threads/blow-detection-using-ios-microphone.118215/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The best starting point looks like &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/10501236/stream-media-from-iphone&quot;&gt;this StackOverflow question&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://audiob.us&quot;&gt;Audiobus&lt;/a&gt; can send audio from one app to another to mix music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is 12:56 AM and I’m pretty tired right now. In the afternoon I have an appointment with my audiologist and I’m going to ask what the risks of this are to my ears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8292016&quot;&gt;8/29/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talked to my audiologist today and she didn’t seem too concerned about my project, other than telling me to avoid prolonged exposure to more than 85 dB. It shouldn’t be difficult to build in a sound check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend recommended that I reach out to professors at R.I.T. It hosts the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Technical_Institute_for_the_Deaf&quot;&gt;National Technical Institute for the Deaf&lt;/a&gt; which is the largest technological college for the deaf and hard-of-hearing so in my friend’s words, “if there’s any group that’s doing research about this stuff, it’s them.” At the very least, they would have a better idea of the latest research, could provide me with better terminology, or lead me to someone else helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8302016&quot;&gt;8/30/2016&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I got an email that my library books were due so I went over and wore the ActivBuds instead of my hearing aid. I’m getting more accustomed to how everything sounds (really weird, btw) and I’m going to the beach this weekend to conduct tests in saltwater. As for building my own app, well, there’s one week left of summer. Realistically, I have never built an iOS app before or written in Swift so between my job, finishing up my last year of school, and job hunting, I can’t see a prototype coming out until next summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the forseeable future, my setup will be the Senso/Petralex pairing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8312016&quot;&gt;8/31/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went to a party today and met a Physics major. We talked about some of the physics of electromagnetic waves. Haven’t really done anything on this project for a couple days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;12032016&quot;&gt;12/03/2016&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been three entire months! I have bad news, good news, and great news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad news: I spilled water on my laptop and didn’t get a new one until yesterday. That’s why I didn’t update for so long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good news: The laptop I got is the new Macbook Pro! I have been working hard all semester and my previous laptop was from 2010, so I felt like I deserved to treat myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great news: The final week of summer, I did several rounds of live field tests: swimming in the pool, swimming in the beach, and swimming in the ocean. In all cases, my project was FUNCTIONAL! It was an amazing time and I went back to school on this high note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a whim, I had also decided to test the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Swimbuds-Waterproof-Headphones-Underwater-Promotion/dp/B006IF7S92/&quot;&gt;Swimbuds&lt;/a&gt; since they are wired and, as a bonus, IPX8-rated. (In comparison, the ActivBuds are IPX7.) Both products were tested in pool and ocean conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beach-senso-activbuds&quot;&gt;Beach: Senso ActivBuds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first trial was an afternoon at the beach with the ActivBuds. Honestly, I had been so excited for the field test that I didn’t even think about the logistics of how I would carry the iPhone while swimming. I had it in the aforementioned waterproof case and hooked it to my bikini on my hip with a carabiner, but that dragged the fabric down. It was so awkward, not to mention the fact that the maximum range was already just 17.31 cm (6.81 in) under the best of conditions so I definitely couldn’t be chest-deep and still expect to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I figured that at least my head should always be above water so I fastened the case to the straps around my neck (with the case hanging on my back). Since the case was buoyant, it just floated behind my head as I waded through the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was calibrating the amplifier. My very patient friend told random stories as I fiddled around. Unfortunately, I can’t remember the exact settings anymore but the sound took quite a bit to get used to. At close range, the amplification was enough to improve my lip reading accuracy. Twenty meters apart, I could not understand anything but could hear my friend yelling out to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, we had swam out pretty far and the ActivBuds withstood some thirty minutes of swimming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pool-swimbuds&quot;&gt;Pool: Swimbuds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second trial was later that day at the pool with the Swimbuds. I hooked the case to my bikini’s neck strap and calibrated the settings with the same friend. WOW. It was a WORLD of difference! The sound quality was far clearer with the wired earbuds and I was able to comprehend my friend with almost perfect comprehension at near range (within one meter). My biggest complaints with the ActivBuds is how different things sounded. All the pitches and tones were completely “off.” With the earbuds, things sounded slightly more normal (but still different).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ocean-senso-activbuds&quot;&gt;Ocean: Senso ActivBuds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, my friend and I decided to try out snorkeling. Neither of us had done it before and this was a perfect setting to push the limits of my experiment. To recap, the ActivBuds held up with my head above water and the phone floating next to my head (yes, it’s an odd sight). With my head underwater the entire time (within the theoretical range), two questions arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does the connection hold up?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will the IPX7 rating hold?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For thirty minutes, my ear was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Connected… Disconnected… Connected… Disconnected…”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that was a big flop. I ended up turning it off and just snorkeling in silence. On the second question, I’m listening to music with the ActivBuds as I write this post, so I can definitely attest to its build quality. Well worth the $33.97 current list price on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ocean-swimbuds&quot;&gt;Ocean: Swimbuds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had such a blast that we went snorkeling again the following day! I brought along the Swimbuds and as expected, there were no connection issues. My head was completely submerged underwater while the phone floated along. We could not talk with the masks on so little verbal communication was needed. After a while, we found a low cave and swam inside. It was almost pitch black and I couldn’t see my friend’s face, but I heard him say, “I’m not comfortable with this.” It is exactly this kind of situation that that this whole project is meant for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field test results exceeded my expectations and I am so happy, but I also feel so silly that the solution was so simple. The semester ends in a few weeks and I want to try other conditions. In the preliminary field tests, my friend was the only audio source; there was no overlapping background chatter. How well would this perform under noisier conditions? Water parks, pool parties, any scenario that involves following overlapping conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, Jacoti Lola was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/jacoti-lola-deployed-at-audacity-603580646.html&quot;&gt;demoed at the AuDacity 2016 audiology convention&lt;/a&gt; as a hearing assistance device that connected over Wifi technology. The reviews were promising:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In addition, 100% of Lola users who had hearing loss reported that Lola improved speech understanding, with a vast majority (86%) reporting that Lola helped “a lot.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company has already has a track record in this space: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacoti.com/listenapp/&quot;&gt;Jacoti ListenApp&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.news-medical.net/news/20150331/Jacoti-releases-first-FDA-registered-medical-device-hearing-aid-application-for-smartphones.aspx&quot;&gt;the first FDA registered medical device&lt;/a&gt; for hearing loss. Their product does not service my severity of hearing loss, but I want to try it out anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4102017&quot;&gt;4/10/2017&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This update is long overdue. In my defense, I was &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; busy because I had an international competition to train for with my team, on top of my job and my schoolwork. Now I just have a few weeks left until the end of the semester :)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over winter break, my family and I went to the Caribbeans and I brought my setup along. There were two possible environments for field testing: the water park complex that my family stayed at and the deep ocean where where a sailboat took us snorkeling. To recap, the Bluetooth ActivBuds have been holding up well in normal use, with a few annoyances. The connection intermittently cuts in and out for brief periods at a time but then works fine the rest of the time. It is possible that some of the internal hardware rusted due to the snorkeling tests from the past summer. They are, after all, IPX7 and not IPX8. As a result, I used the SwimBuds for this set of field tests since they are truly IPX8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logistics were really annoying to deal with during the water park. It was uncomfortable having the iPhone hanging off from my bikini’s shoulder strap and the wires were frustrating to deal with. I also had to recalibrate the microphone several times while walking with my family because I didn’t have any of the presets saved. Once I set it up however, it wasn’t too bad. My family and I went a few rounds on the lazy river and I could hear my family members yelling to each other from their tubes. The intelligibility was pretty bad in the beginning as I was trying to get used to the different sounds. As I got used to it, I could start make out a few words at a time but overall my ability to distinguish speech between people on the tube was poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t much need to talk when snorkeling in the deep ocean. The warbles from the sound of the oceans were REALLY disorienting and I had to turn the volume way down. For the most part, I swam alongside my dad but then off in the distance, I saw my mom struggling with her mask. It seems like both my dad and my brother were too far off in the distance to hear her (and so was I, even with the Swimbuds). By the time I swam up to her, one of the guides from the sailboat had gotten to her and the three of us were all hanging onto a life tube. At that face-to-face distance, I was able to understand the entire conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I am pleased that the Swimbuds continue to perform acceptably when conversation is required in close-proximity conditions. However, the logistics of having to tie a bulky case to my bikini straps is really annoying and I’m always a little bit afraid that the case will fail and damage my phone in the process. At the time of this writing, the current iPhone 7 has an IP67 rating – the same as my ActivBuds. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/news/how-water-resistant-is-the-iphone-7/&quot;&gt;CNET’s field tests&lt;/a&gt;, the iPhone 7 seems to do OK but the iPhone 8 is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cultofmac.com/462289/iphone-8-may-even-higher-waterproof-rating/&quot;&gt;rumored to be IP68&lt;/a&gt; which would be a drastic upgrade. If a future upgrade of Apple AirPods sees an IP67 rating, I will have to try it out and see if the W1 chip in the AirPods results in a better connection quality.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2017/waterproof-hearing-aid</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2017/waterproof-hearing-aid</guid>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>logs</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ode to 0110001101100100</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;You believed in linear projections and initial conditions,  
In neither ergodicity nor embedded good behavior.  
There were no trivial autmorphisms in your infinite measure;
It was not in the heart of your group.

In my vector space I see structure, but I also see manifolds  
Confined not in Cartesian space, but beyond Banach;  
Eclipsing Euclidean, held in Hilbert space and time  
Renouncing these classic decompositions of love.

Though uncertainty infinitely partitioned my heart,  
I sought to create one-to-one correspondence.  
With our log normally distributed as any other process,  
Could I generate moments between us for all time?  

A series grows.

In time, the partial sums of your effort revealed  
The distance disguised by your harmonic terms.  
With neither a limit nor your support,  
I diverge.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This poem arose after I confessed a bit of heartbreak to a mentor of mine. He had stumbled upon the first poem I wrote several years ago and encouraged me to keep writing – the first verse belongs entirely to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time, my studies have progressed deeper into probability theory. Again, I find so many parallels between mathematics and my life. In addition to vector spaces analogies, there are log-normal distributions, moment-generating functions, and divergent series.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2017/0110001101100100</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2017/0110001101100100</guid>
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Liquid Syntax Errors in Jekyll 3.2.1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Two days ago, I encountered the following error message when building my site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Asset inconsitency, expected
jekyll 3.1.6 | Error: undefined method &lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;logical_path&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;' for nil:NilClass
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t encountered this before, so I just ran &lt;code&gt;jekyll clean&lt;/code&gt; which flushed my caches and everything in &lt;code&gt;/_site/&lt;/code&gt;. Well, it fixed the error but then I got a new one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Liquid Exception: Liquid syntax error &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;line 12&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;: Unknown tag &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'img'&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the record, this is how I was inserting images in my Markdown:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;{% &lt;/span&gt;img river-tubing.jpg %&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick and easy. I fixed it with &lt;a href=&quot;https://superdevresources.com/image-caption-jekyll/&quot;&gt;this workaround&lt;/a&gt; (with new image captioning support). Now I would insert images like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;{% &lt;/span&gt;include image.html
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;images/river-tubing.jpg&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;caption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Image from Trinity River Vision Authority.&quot;&lt;/span&gt; %&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was REALLY SAD that the original method didn’t work. Why?! So I upgrade from Jekyll 3.1 to 3.2.1 to see if it worked – it didn’t. Well, then I found out that my images weren’t copying over in Jekyll because they were never being referenced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/17990087/why-images-folder-is-not-copied-when-generating-an-octopress-with-jekyll-assets&quot;&gt;similar complaint&lt;/a&gt; and tried the following solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;{% &lt;/span&gt;asset_path river-tubing.jpg %&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which would give me the following error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Liquid syntax error &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;line 12&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;: Unknown tag &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'asset_path'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s not an issue with Jekyll, it’s an issue with my configuration. At this point I have spent enough time on it and really want to get back to my bluetooth project.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2016/jekyll-liquid-syntax-error</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2016/jekyll-liquid-syntax-error</guid>
        
        <category>bugs</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Summer in Review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Another sun-soaked season comes to a close. I was so happy to “break” into finance this year and it’s been a tremendously interesting internship, owing to some unusual circumstances and a fantastic team. I worked at a large commercial bank on the top floor (well, the C-Suite occupies the floor above us) and I’ll be honest - pressing my floor in the elevator still hasn’t gotten old after 10 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full-time hire started the same day as me and we were both assigned to the same portfolio. Working with him was a learning opportunity in and of itself; he was incredibly proactive with great interpersonal skills, and served as a good example for how to act as a new hire. We both hit the ground running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were on the subprime mortgage and mortgage-backed securities portfolios. Older people will be familiar with how the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subprime_mortgage_crisis&quot;&gt;subprime mortgage crisis&lt;/a&gt; caused the 2007-2009 economic recession. Back then, I was still a kid and before this internship, I barely understood what a mortgage was, let alone what happened. A friend recommended &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1596363/&quot;&gt;The Big Short&lt;/a&gt; to me and I found it an entertaining and educational look at how these did the damage they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the get-go, it felt like I was drinking from the firehose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The learning curve was steep because there was just so much information to swallow in so little time. We needed to pull data from various databases but in order to know what sources to pull it from, we needed to understand what’s in the portfolio and how the assets worked. It wasn’t just a matter of conceptually understanding what a mortgage-backed security was, but understanding it from an accounting perspective and accordingly, how the bank structures its data. I must have read hundreds of pages of documentation and paperwork – if you look in my notebook, you’ll see a ton of flowcharts, graphs, and diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every intern also got a mentor. Mine was one of my interviewers and out of three people, he had asked the toughest technical questions – former math professor, go figure. Looking back, I don’t think I could have had a better mentor! Even though he was a busy person, he often gave me lectures on the spot covering topics from mathematical theory to financial news to the bank’s history. Above all, I think what set him apart was how he didn’t just give me guidance, but also opportunities for me to set myself apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was as simple as giving me exposure to different things by bringing me to all of his meetings, whether or not they related to my current work. In and out of these meetings, he would “go to bat” for me with my manager by recommending additional work for me to take on. It was still up to me to deliver results but with his support, I was able to do a lot in 10 weeks. I am pretty grateful and someday, I want to be to somebody else what he was to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is so much more I could say about this summer, but I want to focus on what I think makes for a successful intern based on the last couple months. Like other things in life, being remembered comes down to two things: having information, and using it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;information-is-power&quot;&gt;Information is Power&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get the information you need.&lt;/strong&gt; One of the senior quants said this to me over and over in my first week and it internalizes a deeper mentality: being proactive. In his context, it was about understanding how subprime mortgages work and figuring that out by not just reading things, but also talking to the portfolio managers, the traders, and the accounting people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being proactive meant asking questions early and asking questions often, going to where the information was instead of waiting for the information to somehow come to you. In a way, this mentality is similar to that of advocating for yourself, which is what every hard-of-hearing and deaf person has had to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good social skills make getting information easier.&lt;/strong&gt; At the core, this skill is about being able to develop chemistry with others.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In the short-term, chemistry not only helps you with getting information from others, but also in collaborating with people on projects. When your coworkers feel natural and comfortable interacting with you, communication is smoother, issues can be addressed more quickly, and direction is clearer when everyone is on the same page. When management likes you, they remember your name and serve as good advisors and mentors.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In the long-term, you learn about prevailing trends, issues, and opportunities to “add value.” Chance, indeed, favors the prepared mind.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be authentic.&lt;/strong&gt; Frankly, developing social skills isn’t easy; it is a muscle that only improves through consistent practice. I think there is so much advice out there that gives shortcuts and “hacks” on “getting people to like you,” which are often executed at the expense of sincerity. On the other end, people champion authenticity but it’s important to realize that being authentic isn’t something you do for other people. Instead, it means having confidence in yourself and believing that there is value in who you are. It means recognizing that you cannot please everybody and being at peace with that. Plus, you do better work when you feel comfortable in your own skin instead of when you’re trying to be somebody you’re not.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;being-indispensible&quot;&gt;Being Indispensible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add value.&lt;/strong&gt; This action can be broken into two components: making yourself indispensible to the company, and making yourself indispensible to other people.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The first component is about improving the company as a whole. Examples include becoming a subject matter expert e.g. on an asset class, or taking initiative on finding ways to improve the bottom line, or taking on a much-needed but ignored issue.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The second component is about making other people’s jobs easier. This can be as straightforward as generating weekly risk reports to your boss &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the way they like to read it, or as altruistic as helping a busy coworker tackle obstacles in their work, or even serving in an advisory or mentorship capacity to others.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write good code, or write good papers.&lt;/strong&gt; Both were a big part of my internship and this seems to be the general trend in the quant space of finance. That leads to the next bullet point…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn to focus without distraction on cognitively demanding tasks.&lt;/strong&gt; You really cannot be a good (quant) intern if you cannot consistently produce work that isn’t easy to reproduce. Focusing on hard things that people unambiguously value, day after day, week after week, is more or less the whole ball game and to do that, you need to learn how to do &lt;a href=&quot;http://calnewport.com/books/deep-work/&quot;&gt;deep work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://x-axis.github.io/2016/quant-internship</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://x-axis.github.io/2016/quant-internship</guid>
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
        <category>finance</category>
        
        <category>internship</category>
        
        <category>jobs</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
